Previously on
Space Brothers
むった
＜不運に縁がある兄･六太＞
Older brother Mutta is plagued by bad luck.
ひびと
＜栄光の日生まれの弟･日々人は➡
Born under a lucky star, younger brother Hibito becomes the first Japanese moonwalker.
日本人初の
ムーンウォーカーとなった＞
おんし
＜月面望遠鏡建設を望む恩師･
シャロンとの約束を果たすため➡
Older brother Mutta seeks to become an astronaut, and keep his promise to former teacher Sharon,
兄･六太は宇宙飛行士を目指す＞
to build a telescope on the moon.
Mutta's made it through the first round, but he keeps running into trouble.
かろ
＜選抜試験を辛うじて突破するが
訓練中もトラブルの連続！＞
＜筆記試験では最低点｡暴走教官が
飛行訓練の担当になる始末＞
On the written test, he scores the lowest.
And as a result, he's assigned to a wild flight instructor.
＜だが 困難に揉まれたおかげで
宇宙飛行士の大事な資質を➡
However, the older brother Mutta
has yet to realize that he's rapidly learning the lessons he'll need to become an astronaut.
猛スピードで身に付けている事に
兄･六太は まだ気づいていない＞
(ジョン)大丈夫か ヒビト！
ヘルメット外すぞ！
You okay, Hibito?
We're removing your helmet.
なんば
(南波日々人)ハァハァハァ｡
君も知っての通り
月ミッションのクルーには➡
As you're well aware,
crew members on lunar missions are required to be available for EVA.
船外活動の技能が
ひっす
必須条件となっている｡
残念だがヒビト｡
船外活動が出来ないうちは➡
I'm sorry to have to tell you this, Hibito.
But we can't send you on lunar missions if you can't participate in EVA.
君を月ミッションには
加えられないんだ｡
この変な症状 必ず治します｡
I'm going to find a way to get rid of this disorder.
それまで この事は
医師と僕たちだけの話に➡
In the meantime, can you keep this a secret among you, me, and the doctors?
とど
留めておいてもらえますか｡
うちの家族…特に兄には｡
Tell my family, particularly my brother...
｢僕は あくまで
月の訓練を続けている｣と｡
that I'm still training for lunar missions.
りょうかい
了解した…医師連中にも➡
Understood.
I'll have the doctors report that you suffer from a temporary physical condition.
一時的な体調不良で通すように
伝えておこう｡
だがヒビト ウソを
つき通すのは しんどいぞ｡
However, Hibito...
It will be difficult to maintain that lie.
(ﾀﾞﾐｱﾝ)地球だと こんなふうな
揺れになるんだけど➡
On Earth, it's only a little bump...
月だとね｡➡
But on the moon, it's kinda like an awkward way to skip.
ヘタクソな
スキップみたいになる｡
ハンドリングにしても
ブレーキの利きにしても➡
If you want to improve the handling or the brakes' efficiency,
改善するためには浮かないように
車体を重くするしかないかな｡
you'll have to make the body heavier, to keep it from becoming airborne.
上から散々｢軽量化 軽量化｣と
言われた末の➡
The body's light because the brass keeps asking us to minimize the weight.
あのホネホネボディーだ
ってことを➡
誰か彼らに説明してあげて｡
Can someone explain that to them?
(南波六太)落ちないバギーかぁ
チクショー｡
A buggy that won't fall, huh?
Damn...
子供ん頃さ 未来じゃ 車も
空 飛んでると思ってたけどなぁ｡
When I was little, I figured we'd have flying cars in the future.
Oh...
何の｢あ｣？
解決できるかもしれない案を➡
Oh, what?
Oh, I might have a solution to our problem.
思いついたかもしれないの｢あ｣｡
(中川)南波先輩!?
Nanba?
俺が昔 大ボツ食らった
｢飛行自動車｣の➡
Remember the flying car I designed that was scrapped?
そう！あれの企画データって
まだ残ってる？
Yes, are those blueprints still around?
までら
(間寺)僕にもちょっと話させて｡
Let me talk to him.
《これはチャンスだ！》
This is my chance!
ああ いいとも！ウチに出来ること
なら 何だって協力するよ｡
That's fine.
We'll assist in any way that we can.
車のプロの実力を
ぜひ宇宙で役立てたいんです｡
I'm excited to send professional engineering into space.
あずま
(吾妻)なぜ六太に志望の月の訓練
をさせないんですか 室長！
So why won't you let Mutta train for a lunar mission, Director?
ヒビトに障害がある以上➡
If Mutta begins training for a lunar mission while Hibito is suffering from a disorder,
ムッタが月の訓練を
始めるということは➡
あせ
ヒビトの焦りと不安をあおり➡
Hibito will only feel more pressure, and curing him will be harder.
パニック障害治療の
さまた
妨げになってしまうんだ｡
俺は逆だと思いますけどね｡
I think they have it backward.
プレゼンを始めるにあたって➡
Mutta has a request to make before the presentation begins.
六太さんから
ご要望がありまして｡
Hmm?
ふむ｡
(職員)もし この改良案を
気に入っていただけて➡
If you like the proposal and deem it feasible,
実現可能と判断された場合➡
月の訓練への参加を検討して
いただきたい…とのことです｡
he wants you to let him train for a lunar mission.
ふん ずいぶん強気だな｡
まぁ そんな約束は出来んが｡
Heh, he sounds pretty confident.
Well, I can't make any promises.
ジョンソンスペースセンターへ
お願いします｡
Johnson Space Center, please.
(ﾄﾞﾗｲﾊﾞｰ)オーケイ！
Okay.
Peter looks pretty relaxed...
《のんびりしてんな ピーターは》
《プレゼン前とは思えん》
Hard to believe he's going to a presentation.
(ダン)今日は頼むぜ リーダー｡
We're counting on you, leader.
《リーダーとも思えん》
Hard to believe he's the leader.
俺は君達と違って優秀だから➡
I'm a lot smarter than the rest of you.
プレゼンの流れなんて
とっくに頭に入ってんの｡
I already have the presentation in my head.
ていうか話す相手は お偉い
オッサン達しか いないでしょ｡
And we'll just be presenting to a bunch of important old men, right?
スタイルのいい女の子が
一人でもいればさぁ➡
If there were a hot babe watching, I might try a little harder...
俺も もうちょい
気合い いれるんだけどね｡
(中川)失礼します｡
Excuse us.
お待たせ｡
Sorry to keep you waiting.
It's just obvious that the more you put in your bag
The heavier it gets
The harder I work, the closer I get to my goal
But I'm just not getting there fast enough
I gaze at the night sky but it doesn't calm me down
Now that you've heard how loud my heart's beating
Let's take a trip outside
My starvation knows no bounds under this sea of stars
In this planetarium of dreams and reality
I'm currently updating the canvas of my dreams
With a glittering universe and a blue earth
My starvation knows no bounds under this sea of stars
In this planetarium of facades and honesty
I'm currently conversing with the canvas of my dreams
On this orbit of fate
With a fire in my belly
#73 A Road on the Roadless Moon
Remember when Hibito fell in the ravine,
日々人が月で谷に落ちた時➡
スリーディー
３Ｄの地形マップを
見せてくれましたよね｡
and you showed me that 3D lunar map?
そう あれです｡同じように
｢かぐやⅡ｣が観測した➡
Yeah, that.
I'm looking for similar data from Kaguya II for the entire area around Moonbase.
月面基地周辺の地形データが
欲しいんです｡
ほしか
なるほど わかった すぐ送るよ｡
I see... I understand.
I'll send it over right away.
あ ありがとうございます！
[ｹｲﾀｲ](星加)それより六太君｡
Thank you very much!
Also, Mutta...
もうすぐ その
｢かぐやⅡ｣の観測データから➡
Huh?
Using data from Kaguya II,
we're about to complete a new lunar surface map.
新しい月面マップが出来るんだ｡
よし はじめてくれ｡
Okay, go ahead.
I'm already a nervous wreck with all the top dogs watching us...
《お偉いさん達の視線により➡
ただでさえ
緊張するというのに…➡
吾妻さんがいるせいで
プレッシャーが５割増しに…》
Azuma's presence only increases the pressure.
《頼むぜ ピーター…俺の行く末は
バギー製作のリーダーである➡
Come on, Peter...
My future rests on your speech as buggy development team leader.
あんたのスピーチに
かかってんだ｡➡
So don't just stand there like an idiot.
だから その
ボーッとした顔やめろ！》
I would like to thank everyone for joining us here today, to hear our presentation.
本日は我々のために➡
わざわざ このような
プレゼン会議にお集まり頂き➡
誠にありがとうございます｡
今日のために そして宇宙飛行士…
もとい！ＮＡＳＡのために➡
We have pooled ideas, and even fought at times...
All for this moment, for the astronauts, and for NASA.
我々は知恵を出し合い
殴り合うこともありました｡➡
そして 死に物狂いで
死に物狂いで…➡
And after a grueling amount of effort,
we've finally come up with an answer.
ようやく答えに
たどり着いた訳です｡➡
And what is our proposed answer?
さて 我々の考え出した案が
一体どんなものなのか？➡
一体あの月面バギーを
どのようにすれば➡
What will it take to make the lunar buggy safer for astronauts?
宇宙飛行士の安全が確保される
のか！気になるでしょ？➡
Interested? I'm sure you must be.
気になりますよね？
説明しましょう｡
We will explain everything!
よし！言ってやれ｡
Okay! Explain away.
Bastard...
《おのれ…》
え～ ウホンッ！
まず ブレーキやタイヤではなく➡
First, we wouldn't be changing the brakes or tires.
Instead, we will modify the suspension, so that the rover bounces less.
月面で跳ねにくくするために
サスペンションを➡
少～し改良する必要があります｡➡
これには 現地での作業というのが
一番手っ取り早いでしょう｡
The easiest method would be to make the adjustments on the moon.
If you send an astronaut who can do auto work to the moon, it'd be a quick job.
車をいじれる宇宙飛行士が
月へ行けば すぐ済みます｡
(役員)車をいじれる宇宙飛行士？
ウホンッ！
An astronaut who can do auto work?
For example...
あ～ 例えばまあ 僕のような…
ウホンッ！んんっ…｡
Someone like me...
And this is our idea for preventing accidents in the future.
そして 事故を無くすために
必要なのは こちら！
船外活動用ヘルメットの
バイザーと同じ➡
A windshield made from polycarbonate, like the visors on spacesuit helmets.
ポリカーボネート製の
ﾌﾛﾝﾄｳｨﾝﾄﾞｳを取り付けます｡
フロントウィンドウ？
(役員)どういうことだね？
A windshield?
What's that for?
10 days earlier
Japanese roads are always jammed.
日本の道路は渋滞天国でね｡
こりゃもういよいよ
空を使うしかねえなと思って➡
So I figured we'd have to turn to the skies,
子供ん頃に想像してた➡
and I came up with a plan to make my dream of flying cars reality.
空飛ぶ車社会を
実現させようという試みでさ➡
｢飛行自動車計画｣って企画書作って
上司に提出したことがある｡
I wrote up a flying automobile proposal, and I submitted it to my boss.
(ｳｨﾝｽﾄﾝ)マジかよ？
Seriously?
そりゃまた
ブッ飛んだことしたねえ｡
That was a crazy thing to do.
ま アメリカにも それを夢見て➡
Well, plenty of weirdos in America have designed flying cars already...
空飛ぶ車を作っちゃってる
モノ好きは たくさんいるけど➡
But I always wondered how they planned to control the traffic.
交通の秩序を空に
どう構築するつもりなのかは➡
いつも疑問に思うね｡
車は飛ばせても
道路は飛ばせない｡
You can make cars fly, but not the roads.
その企画書じゃ
どうするつもりだったんだ？
What did you propose?
How were you going to put traffic lights and signs in the air?
信号やら標識を
どうやって空にとどめとく？
日本にはあるんじゃない？
そういう技術｡
Maybe Japan has the technology to do it?
空は空のまま
な～んもいらねえんだ｡
We leave the sky untouched.
Nothing changes.
Huh?
飛ぶのは車だけ｡あとはそれぞれの
フロントガラスに➡
We make the cars fly...
Then we display virtual roads on the windshield.
架空の共通道路を映し出せばいい｡
へえ…｡
My boss shot down the idea as unrealistic...
まあ 上司からは現実味がないって
はねのけられたんだけどね｡
But my idea to display roads on the windshield gave rise
フロントガラスに道を投影する
案は活かすことになって➡
to the development of a system to display navigation tools there instead.
カーナビをフロントガラスに
映す計画になってったんだ｡
Well, I was fired while the system was still in development...
ま 俺はその計画中に
クビになった訳だけど…できた！
All done!
つまり ムッタの案は バギーにも
そういうﾌﾛﾝﾄｶﾞﾗｽをつけると？
So your idea is to use that windshield on the buggy?
そう！
Yep!
We can create roads on the roadless moon!
道なき月面に道を映し出す｡
どうよ？この案｡
できたらすげえよな｡
What do you think?
If we can make it work, it'd be amazing.
ハハッ｡まあね できたらな｡
仮説としては面白い｡
I guess... If it works.
At least, it's an interesting hypothesis.
面白いが あくまでそれは仮説だ｡
コスト的 時間的
技術的に見ても➡
But it's nothing more than a hypothesis.
When you look at the required cost, time, and technology,
the proposal is too big for us.
私達には途方もなく
大きすぎる計画だね｡
《チッ！》
でも 今みんなが笑ったことが
もし実現できたらさ｡
You may scoff now, but if I can make it happen...
誰も文句言わなくなるよ｡
Then no one will be able to complain.
We're building something new.
新しいモノ作ろうって話なんだ｡
最初はなんだって｢仮説｣だろ｡
You always start with a hypothesis, right?
There's one thing we must avoid.
現在
回避したいものは ひとつだけ｡
ヒビトとダミアンが言っていた➡
Hibito and Damian mentioned that
the moon's lack of landmarks means you can run into craters or ravines without warning.
目印になるものがない月面で
突然現れるクレーターや谷です｡
このフロントウィンドウに
安全に走れるルートを映せば➡
If we display safe routes on the windshield,
astronauts will be able to avoid craters and ravines as they move around.
宇宙飛行士は ｸﾚｰﾀｰや谷を避けて
移動できるという訳です｡
どうです？完璧でしょ？
Thoughts? It's perfect, yes?
まあ アイデアとしては面白いが
コストはどうなる？
Well, it's certainly an interesting idea, but what would it cost?
How do we develop a lunar navigation system?
そもそも月面ナビなんてもの
どうやって作る？
I can imagine that kind of technology costing a fortune.
その技術開発だけで 莫大な予算が
かかるんじゃないのかね？
お願いします！
Please come in!
(糸井)失礼します｡
Hello.
何だ？誰？
What? Who are they?
失礼します｡
Hello.
何だ？誰？
What? Who are they?
コホン｡ええ ご紹介しましょう｡
彼らは日本の自動車開発会社➡
Let me introduce you.
These are engineers from Miracle Car, a Japanese automobile company.
ミラクルカーの技術チーム
中川君と糸井君です｡
This is Nakagawa.
And Itoi.
私が以前勤めていた会社の
社員で➡
I used to be an employee at their company,
タダ同然の契約料で協力して
もらっているので ご安心を｡
and they've signed a contract to work for nearly nothing, so cost isn't a concern.
なんと…｡
Really?
ありがと｡
(糸井)よろしくお願いします｡
Thank you.
No need to thank us.
We're looking forward to this.
《懐かしいな この感じ》
It's been a while since I've been this excited.
(中川)《南波先輩とまた➡
I get to work with Nanba again.
こうやって一緒に
仕事をすることになるなんて…》
A cluster fan engine?
クラスターファンエンジン？
Right...
そうそう｡このエンジン技術を
使えば 普通サイズの車でも➡
With this type of engine, it's theoretically possible for a normally sized car to fly.
理論上は
自由に空を飛べるようになる｡
小さなファンの集合体を
車のフロント部分➡
A sky-car with a cluster of small fans at the front, and wings at the back...
そして後部に搭載した
翼付きのスカイカー…｡
空飛ぶ車か～ 僕も子供の頃は
こんな車 考えてましたよ｡
A flying car?
When I was a kid, I dreamed about that.
Even now, it's still a dream...
未だに夢物語ですよね｡
未来の話って感じで｡
Something we may see in the future.
でも 子供の頃の俺らからしたらさ
今ってもう その未来だよ｡
But if that was when we were kids,
then we're already in the future now.
＜僕達 社員に
与えられていた課題は➡
Our task was dealing with fuel consumption inefficiencies stemming from heavy traffic.
｢渋滞による燃費悪化の解消｣｡➡
In other words, we had to design a high-mileage car that could handle Japan's busy traffic.
つまりは 日本の渋滞事情にも
負けない➡
低燃費を売りにできるような➡
新たな車の案を
提出することだった＞
うわぁ…ううっ…うん！
That was when you proposed that we develop a flying car, eliminating traffic jams altogether.
＜ところが南波先輩は➡
渋滞そのものを無くす
空飛ぶ車社会と➡
そのさきがけとなる車を
提案しようなどと言い出した＞
南波君の案は夢があって
良いと思うんだけどさ…｡
I was impressed by the foresight Nanba's idea demonstrated.
でも やっぱり
突飛すぎるんじゃない それ｡
But it's too far-fetched...
ウチも他のチームも
現実的な案を練ってるし➡
The other teams have all developed more practical ideas,
君らのその案じゃ
全く相手にされないと思うよ｡
so your proposal will probably be ignored.
Well, you're probably right.
(中川)まぁ そうかも
しれないんですけど｡
Don't Feed
the Pigeons
他 行ってくれね～かな君達｡
Can't you guys go away?
(中川)あっ いた！南波先輩！
Oh, there he is...
Nanba!
今は当たり前に
乗ってる車も飛行機もさ➡
The cars and planes that we see everywhere were once considered pipe dreams.
昔は夢の乗り物だったと
思うんだよ｡
今 俺達が空飛ぶ車は
夢物語だって思ってるみたいに｡
The same way everyone thinks our flying car is a pipe dream.
いつか誰かが
空飛ぶ車を実現させて➡
One day, someone will make a flying car reality, and a part of everyday life,
当たり前にすると思うんだけど｡
それが俺達になる
可能性もあるんだよ？
and it could very well be us.
それ彼女の手作り？
Did your girlfriend make that?
い いやぁ～自分で…｡
ふ～ん かわいそ｡
Uh, n-no, I made it...
Loser.
Well, I'm sure he'll understand one day.
まぁ彼にも
いずれ分かる日が来る｡
《もしかしたら南波先輩は➡
We always wondered if you felt you had to achieve something great
宇宙飛行士になるという
偉業を果たした➡
弟の日々人さんに
負けないほどの偉業を➡
because your brother had become an astronaut.
自分でも成し遂げ
たかったのかもしれない》
《僕達はそんな事を考えつつも
ただなんとなく南波先輩と➡
But at the same time, we really enjoyed working with you.
仕事をするのが
楽しいと感じていた》
初期段階では
飛行機と同じように➡
At first, cars would be restricted to certain lanes, similar to air traffic control.
飛行経路を限定します｡
飛行自動車用の空港を
数箇所 設定して➡
We would begin by placing airports specifically for flying cars,
空港への区間のみの飛行を
実践してくイメージです｡
then test flights between those airports.
(間寺)ま～た随分
恥ずかしいくらいの➡
You've brought me a grand and crazy idea, Nanba.
壮大なアイデアを持ってきたね
南波くん｡
Th-Thank you very much!
あ ありがとうございます｡
別に褒めてないよ｡
That wasn't a compliment.
だいたい車を低燃費にする
アイデアを募ってるのに➡
You were tasked to improve fuel efficiency,
空飛ばしてどうすんの｡
so why suggest flying cars?
That would worsen fuel efficiency.
どんだけ燃費が
悪くなるんだよ｡
Oh, yes.
あっ はい
燃料についてはもちろん➡
The plan considers ways to reduce fuel consumption down the line.
将来的なプランも考えまして…
Forget it... That's enough.
いやいや もういいよ｡
趣旨が違うから｡
You've completely missed the point.
悪いけど飛行自動車の企画は➡
This flying car proposal should be a convention presentation.
その手のイベントで
発表してよ｡
あ はい｡
Oh, right...
《ダメか…》
No luck, huh?
でもフロントウィンドウの案は
すごく面白いと思ったよ｡
But we were fascinated by the windshield idea.
確かに｡
Indeed.
Huh? Eh?
えっ あっ ですよね？
Ah! Of course.
I was impressed by that part...
私も その部分に関しては
いいかなと｡
The time has finally come for our hard work to pay off.
現在
あの時の僕らの頑張りが
役立てる時が来ましたね｡
あぁ 君らのおかげだよ｡
Yeah, all thanks to you guys.
Let's get started.
(中川)それでは始めます｡➡
え～ご覧の動画は
今 我が社で開発している➡
This video was taken during a test drive, using our company's Front Navigation System.
フロントナビシステムを
搭載した車で撮った➡
試験運転の映像です｡
Left turn coming up.
(ナビ)まもなく左方向です｡
ご覧のように
マップや案内の方向指示などを➡
As you see, you can check maps and orientation without taking your eyes off the road.
視線を下げることなく
確認できるというものです｡
なるほど～｡
Ah...
既に技術としては
ほぼ完成しています｡
And the technology for this system is more or less complete.
これを応用すれば➡
Adapting it to project paths on the lunar rover's windshield would be simple.
月面ローバーの
フロントウィンドウに➡
道を投影させる事は
容易に出来ます｡
(中川)月面地形マップのデータも
あるそうなので➡
It appears that topographic maps of the moon's surface are available, so developing a navigation system is possible.
月面ナビの制作も可能です｡
ちょっと
月面地形マップのデータって何？
Hold on...
What are these topographic maps you mention?
それは私がお答えします｡
I can answer that.
ジャクサ
ＪＡＸＡの
｢かぐやⅡ｣が観測した➡
A new 3D map of the moon has been created with data from JAXA's Kaguya II.
膨大な地形情報から作った➡
新しい月面の３Ｄマップです｡
現在
月の３５％の範囲までであれば➡
Currently, detailed information exists on crater location and depth, for thirty-five percent of the moon.
クレーターの位置や深さまで➡
かなり詳細に
閲覧することが出来ます｡
ＪＡＸＡの成果と
開発会社の技術➡
With JAXA's data
and private technology,
あとＮＡＳＡに熱意さえあれば➡
we only need NASA's passion
我々の この案は実現できます！
for this plan to work!
It's been so long since I looked up at the moon
Though it's always keeping a cold eye on me
Yeah, it always keeps a cold eye on me
I wanna rough up this rotten way home
But even if it makes me mad
I can't take my eyes off it. Yeah, I can't take my eyes off it
I can't take my eyes off that dazzling smile
What did I want back then?
What was I looking for?
I should've known my tears would take me to my dreams
Blow this gloomy reality away for me
I want to see how tiny our huge worries seem
From up in that dark ocean of space
Next time, on
Space Brothers
#74 Magic Trick
I need Director Butler's approval before I can go to the moon.
＜月へ行くには バトラー室長に
認めてもらうしかない＞
＜どうすればいいのか考える中
私は➡
As I consider what to do next, I learn of an aerial maneuver called the vertical climb roll.
ﾊﾞｰﾃｨｶﾙｸﾗｲﾑﾛｰﾙという
ｼﾞｪｯﾄ機の飛行法に たどり着く＞
Next time, on Space Brothers:
"Magic Trick"
Mr. Hibbit!
We've been asked to send a mission to the moon to search for UFOs.
検討されてきた
月面でのＵＦＯ探しミッション！
ついに そのメンバーを
このワシが！
I have just finished selecting the crew for that mission.
いや 私が決定した｡
ニンジン食べる!?
Want some carrots?
Could you listen to me?
いや聞いて｡
まずキャプテンは経験と統率力➡
First, I've chosen the captain for his experience, leadership, and calm demeanor...
冷静さにおいて誰にも負けない➡
Freddy Dog.
フレディドッグ！
Bow wow... I have a sharp nose.
私は鼻がきくんでな｡
ニンジン食べる？
今は投げるな｡
Want some carrots?
Don't throw it.
今日は こいつを紹介する｡
Allow me to introduce you.
仕事の早さはハヤブサ級｡
He works as fast as a falcon.
でもハヤブサじゃないよ｡
ダミアンホーク｡
But he's no falcon.
He's Damian Hawk.
僕は争いを好まない｡
I shun conflict.
これは君に返すよ｡
Let me return this.
それ食べていいよ｡
You can eat it...
If you took a bite, I don't want it.
くわえたやつは
もう いらないよ｡
See you next week!